In this lecture, we'll cover virtual memory and TLBs.
Consider the memory hierarchy that we've discussed so far.
Now what happens when we want to run multiple programs or processes on the same CPU?
Today when we compile a program, we might start executing from address 0 and have the
stack set to a known address towards the top of the range.
If Process A wants to access memory address 1,000 in its program, it assumes it can because
it thinks it's operating in isolation.
How could it possibly know that Process A nor C isn't already using address 1,000?
Do all three programs somehow need to be compiled together in order to run on the same machine
and share the same memory?
Better yet, does this mean that Process A can read any arbitrary data that Process B and
C are using?
Our typical memory hierarchy is built for hardware performance.
However, we have yet to consider what the software program wants.
From that perspective, there are three key things.
First, we want to be able to write programs as if we had an arbitrary amount of memory.
My program shouldn't have to be rewritten or recompiled every time somebody changes
the amount of memory in my machine.
Second, we want to feel like we're the only program running on the system.
As we saw in the previous slide, the memory addresses that my program uses should not
be dependent on the memory addresses that your program uses.
And third, we want to make sure that no other program is able to read, write, or execute
my program's information because they could either steal my private data or they could
break my operation.
How can we provide all of this?
The answer is to virtualize our memory.
Specifically, we want to decouple the address space that the program uses, which is known
as the virtual address space, from the physical addresses that actually exist in the hardware.
So now we have two sets of addresses.
Virtual addresses describe the locations of data from the program's perspective, while
the physical addresses describe the actual locations of data in the memory storage.
When we say we have a 32-bit machine, for example, we are specifically revering to the
number of bits in our virtual addresses.
Physical addresses are generally smaller since the maximum amount of physical memory
that the hardware can support is often smaller than the size of the virtual address space.
For instance, the processor in the single-board computer Raspberry Pi 5 is 64-bit, as is the
latest-generation AMD EPIC data center processor.
While the EPIC supports more address bits than the Raspberry Pi, neither support the
full 64-bit range.
Virtual memory operates at a page granularity to reduce the amount of hardware required
to map between virtual and physical.
That is, both the virtual and physical address spaces are decomposed into pages, which are
relatively large regions of memory, often on the order of 4K or more.
So the idea is that each page in the program's virtual address space is mapped and stored
in some arbitrary location in physical memory.
The pages don't need to be stored contiguously, as in page one and page two won't necessarily
be next to each other in physical memory.
And since main memory may not be very large, any excess pages that we don't use as often
will be stored in disk instead.
And when we eventually do need them, we'll swap them into main memory.
Virtual memory should almost look like another cache, except in this case the blocks are
huge pages, it's fully associative, there's no hardwired replacement policy as it's all
managed by the operating system, and the write policy looks like a write back write
allocate cache.
So at a high level, virtual memory offers automatic transparent memory management with
four key benefits.
The first is program isolation.
This allows each process to think that it's the only one in the system, so it can pre-define
its addresses, such as the stack pointer.
The second is multi-programming.
This mapping allows our system to now run multiple processes at the same time, without
any fear of them clobbering each other's data.
Memory protection is the third benefit.
This virtual to physical mapping can be leveraged to track additional information, like permission
bits for each page.
In this way, our OS can give special permission to specific pages, like read-only data or
non-executable stack regions, to provide memory protection.
This also enables smooth inter-process communication.
Processes can share data by simply mapping one of their own virtual ad pages to a common
physical page.
These are known as synonym pages.
We'll discuss the concept of synonyms in a few minutes.
So how do we perform the address translation from the virtual address to the physical address?
Similar to how we index into caches, we break up the bits of the memory address.
As shown at the bottom, the most significant bits of the virtual address specify the virtual
page number, or VPN, while the least significant bits specify the byte offset within the page.
The VPN is then translated into a physical page number, or PPN.
The page offset bits are untouched because all they do is specify where within the page
each byte is located.
And since data is mapped at a page granularity, a piece of data that is 8 bytes from the beginning
of its virtual address page will still be 8 bytes from the beginning of its physical
page in memory.
In the example shown below, we assume our pages are 64k in size, and log 64k means we
have 16 page offset bits.
If we're using a 32-bit machine, then our virtual addresses are 32 bits wide, thus the
VPN is 16 bits.
And if we have 256 megs of physical memory, that means our physical address is 28 bits
wide, thus our PPN is only 12 bits.
So for 256 megs, the goal of address translation is to simply convert the 16-bit VPN into a
12-bit PPN.
And to do that, we use page tables.
Address translation is generally performed in the OS software, and is referred to as
a page walk.
Each process is allocated a page table, whose role is to remember the PPN of every single
VPN that the program is using.
How it works is that the OS has a pointer to the beginning of the page table.
With that, the VPN is simply used to index into a specific entry in the page table.
Each page table entry contains several things.
The first is the PPN, so that now we know where to find this page in physical memory.
Second is a valid bit, which specifies whether or not this page currently resides in physical
memory.
If we find that it's invalid, then this is considered a page fault, which I'll discuss
on the next slide.
Each page table entry also contains additional information like dirty bits for writebacks
and permission bits for protection.
A page fault occurs when the page we're looking for is currently not in physical memory.
Instead, it's in disk.
So like a typical cache, we must now choose a page to kick out a physical memory and swap
our requested page in.
The OS is responsible for performing these page swaps and must carefully balance the
needs of all running processes to ensure fairness.
Reading a page from disk is generally a super long process, so the OS will often schedule
something else to run on the CPU in the meantime.
It's important to note that each page table is not a dedicated new hardware structure.
Page tables are in fact themselves stored in physical memory.
However, they're generally not subject to address translations since page tables are
only ever accessed by the OS, which has full control of the system similar to the programs
we've written on bare metal MIPS processors.
So if we have a 32-bit machine with 4K pages and each entry in our page table is 4 bytes
wide, then how much storage space do we need to store the page table itself?
With a 32-bit machine, this means our entire virtual address space is 4 gigs, and if each
page is 4K in size, then that means our virtual address space contains 1 million virtual pages
in total.
So that must mean that our page table would need 1 million entries, thus we need 4 megabytes
for the entire page table.
Now dedicating megabytes of storage for the page table can be quite costly, especially
when physical memory is limited.
The common technique to reduce the storage requirements is to use multi-level page tables.
The idea is to form a tree of page tables.
At the last level, which is the L2 shown here, the tables contain the page table entries
that hold the PPN, permission bits, etc.
Because each entry in the earlier page tables simply contain pointers to a later level table.
Then different bits of the VPN are used to index into the different level page tables.
Generally, the first level uses the most significant bits of the VPN.
So let's look at an example.
Assume a 32-bit machine with a 2-level page table with 4K pages, and assume that the page
table entries are 4 bytes in size, and each level 2 page table is 4K in size.
So how much storage is needed?
Since the L2 is the last level in this case, then given that each L2 page table is 4K in
size and each entry is 4 bytes, then we know that there are 1,000 entries per L2 table,
which means that 10 bits of the VPN are used as the L2 index.
Then knowing that the page offset need 12 bits for 4K pages, we find that 10 bits are
used to index into the L1 page table.
That implies that there are 1,000 entries in the L1 page table, each of which could point
to a 1,000 entry L2 page table, where each entry is 4 bytes.
Thus, the total storage requirement is 4 megabytes.
But wait, this is the same size as our single-level page table implementation for earlier.
So how come we haven't really saved any space?
The key observation is that most programs have large regions of pages in the virtual
address space that remain unused throughout their execution.
This makes sense because programs are very unlikely to use up all 4 gigs of their address
space in a 32-bit processor.
So if some regions are never used, then we don't need to allocate page tables for them.
Their corresponding first-level pointers would just remain null.
This way, we're able to eliminate much of the unnecessary storage.
Continuing from the previous example, say our program only uses 2 megabytes of code,
64K of stack, and 16 megs of heap, then roughly how much storage is used for the entire 2-level
page table.
So from earlier, we computed that each L2 page table holds 1,000 entries, so with 4K
pages, that means each L2 page table is capable of translating 4 megs of virtual memory.
So then assuming that the code, heap, and stack are in different locations in the address
space, this program will need 1 L2 page table for the code region, 1 L2 page table for the
stack, and 4 L2 page tables for the heap.
In total, that's only 6 L2 page tables, which is a mere 24K of storage.
The problem is that before every cache access, we need to translate our program's virtual
address to a physical one, so that means we have to walk the page table on every single
load, store, and instruction fetch, which would be very expensive.
So because processor architects love caches almost as much as they love 3-letter acronyms,
the typical solution is to cache recent addresses using a translation look-aside buffer or TLB.
A TLB is a small set associative cache that only contains page table entries, so the VPN,
not the entire virtual address, is broken into a tag and set to index into the TLB.
Note that the TLB doesn't take in any offset bits because each block is just one page table
entry.
The organization is shown below.
On a memory access, we first perform a lookup in the TLB.
If there's a TLB hit, then we'll have the physical page number right away.
Otherwise, we have to walk the page tables.
Note that in addition to the TLB, since the page table is just an array in memory, page
table entries themselves can actually be cached in the regular cache hierarchy to speed up
the page walks.
A common performance metrics for TLBs is TLB reach.
This is saying how much of your virtual address base can the TLB translate at any moment.
This is equal to the number of TLB entries times the size of each page.
So if our TLB holds 64 entries and the page size is 4k, then our TLB is capable of translating
up to 256k of virtual memory at any moment.
In the last part of this lecture, we'll cover the different modes of indexing into caches.
So far, we've assumed a physical cache hierarchy, as shown on the right.
These caches, therefore, are physically indexed, physically tagged, or PIPT.
This means that both the set index bits and the tag bits are derived from the physical
address.
That's why we have to access the TLB prior to accessing the L1 cache.
The advantage of a PIPT is that it's very easy to support inter-process communication,
as in, shared physical pages among different processes.
Such pages can actually be cached without any issues, because with a physical cache,
we're guaranteed to have only one copy of a shared block at a time.
We'll elaborate on this in a bit.
The downside is that we need to perform address translation even when there's a cache hit,
which can significantly slow down our execution time, even if it means just adding one cycle
of latency to our hit.
The alternative is to use virtual caches, which are virtually indexed and virtually
tagged, or VIVT.
As implied, both the set index and tag bits are derived purely from the virtual address
now.
So this means that if we had virtual L1 caches, as shown on the right, then we only need to
perform address translation upon an L1 miss, which is far less frequent.
However, this comes with two key disadvantages.
First, virtual caches have to deal with homonyms.
These are virtual addresses that happen to be the same, but belong to different processes,
so they actually access different physical pages.
If both processes are using the same virtual cache, then they would confuse their data
with each other.
To alleviate this, we'd either have to flush the cache every time we switch execution to
a different process, or we'd have to embed the process ID along with our cache tags.
The second problem is synonyms, which as discussed before, are physical pages that are shared
by different processes, so they use different virtual addresses per process.
To handle synonyms properly, we'd again either have to flush the cache on a process
switch, or try to dynamically detect them in hardware.
To try to get the best of both worlds, we can implement a virtually indexed physically
tagged cache, or VIPT.
In this case, we access the TLB in parallel to the cache lookup.
Specifically, we use the virtual address to compute the set index, and then we perform
a lookup in the tag array.
In parallel, we access the TLB to figure out what the physical address is, and then use
a physical tag to check if our block is in the cache.
This is just as fast as the virtual cache, incurring no additional latency to cache hits
since TLB accesses are generally much faster than cache accesses, since TLBs are much smaller.
This also overcomes the problem of homonyms, we'll never compute pages from two different
processes anymore, because even if they have the same virtual address, we'd still be able
to distinguish them via their physical tags.
However, synonyms may still be a problem.
So let's dive deeper into synonyms to ask why they may still be a problem.
So if virtual addresses X and Y are synonyms and map to the same physical page, then what
happens if we put them into separate locations in the cache?
If we perform a write to X, then we won't propagate that modification to Y, since the
cache is treating them as distinct blocks.
Thus this defeats the purpose of sharing physical pages.
To solve this, the insight is that this wouldn't actually be a problem in a VIPT cache if both
X and Y were to map to the same set in the cache.
Because as long as they're in the same set, then we'll be able to recognize them as the
same block because we'd be checking their physical tags.
So we'd want to design our VIPT cache such that for any pair of synonyms X and Y, the
set index of X is equal to the set index of Y.
The concept sounds simple, but the problem is that we don't know X and Y in advance.
As in, we can't predict where the OS will place shared pages in different processes
virtual address space.
So how can we guarantee that the two synonyms will always end up in the same set?
Well, let's look at an example.
Today we have 4K pages.
If X and Y are synonyms and map to the same physical address, 1A318ED4, is there anything
that we know for sure about X and Y?
We do know that if X and Y map to the same physical address, then their page offset bits,
in this case, their least 12 significant bits, must be identical.
As if you recall from our earlier slides, the page offset bits are untouched during
the address translation process.
So when we're building our VIPT cache, all we have to do is make sure that the set index
bits are among the page offset bits of the virtual address.
This now guarantees that any two synonymous addresses will always land in the same set
in the cache.
Let's wrap up as we always do with a toy exercise.
Consider a 32-bit processor with three level page tables.
Assume that the number of entries in each L1, L2, and L3 page table is 128, 64, and 256,
respectively.
And assume we have a TLB with 512 entries.
So then what is the TLB reach?
Recall how we defined TLB reach.
Please take a moment now and try to compute it.
So, given the number of L1, L2, and L3 entries, we can figure out how many bits are used for
the page offset, which in this case is 11.
So if we have 11 page offset bits, then this must mean that our pages are 2k in size.
Thus, our TLB reach is 1 mb.